<preface id="ch_intro">
<title>Introduction</title>

<section id="ch_intro_history">
<title>History</title>

<para>
The Community OpenORB has its roots in the Distributed Object Group's
<ulink url="http://dog.team.free.fr/index_javaorb.html">JavaORB</ulink>, a pure-Java, 
open-source CORBA ORB.
</para>
<para>The JavaORB project was initiated by Jerome Daniel in October 1998. Only six 
months later, in April 1999, version 1.0 was released. In the same month he founded the Distributed 
Object Group (DOG) together with Xavier Blanc, Nicolas Charpentier, and Vincent 
Vallee. In May 1999 negotiations with ExOffice Technologies, Inc., about a strategic partnership 
started for cooperatively developing new versions of the JavaORB project. In July 1999 version 2.0 
of the JavaORB was released. During the following months several CORBA services and various 
enhancements to the JavaORB's core were added. In February 2000 Olivier Modica joined the DOG team 
and until May 2000 the whole DOG became part of ExOffice Technologies, Inc., Around the same time 
Chris Wood, an employee aith ExOffice Technologies, Inc., joined the team. In June 2000 
the company ExOffice Technologies, Inc., was renamed to Intalio, Inc., In July 2000 the DOG at 
Intalio, Inc., was extended by another member, Marina Daniel.
<footnote>
<para>
<ulink url="http://dog.team.free.fr/about_dog.html">History of the Distributed Object Group (DOG)</ulink>
</para>
</footnote>.
The whole team was working on a new version of the JavaORB which was later renamed to OpenORB. After 
several months of in-house development OpenORB was released 
at <ulink url="http://dog.intalio.com/">www.openorb.org</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
<table frame='all'><title>Release History
<footnote>
<para>
<ulink url="http://cmeerw.org/freeorbwatch/archive/2001.html">OpenORB releases in 2001</ulink>
</para>
</footnote>
</title>
<tgroup cols='2'>
<thead>
<row>
  <entry align="center">Version</entry>
  <entry align="center">Release Date</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
  <entry>1.0.0</entry>
  <entry>February 5th 2001</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>1.0.1</entry>
  <entry>March 9th 2001</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>1.1.0</entry>
  <entry>May 8th 2001</entry>
</row>
<row>
  <entry>1.2.0</entry>
  <entry>August 15th 2001</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
After nine months the OpenORB project had proven to be successful.
Public visibility was increasing steadily and the community had grown to a respectable size.
</para>

<para>
Then the dot.com bubble bursted and many companies, incl. Intalio, Inc., had to focus on their core 
business, in order to survive. It 
became obvious to the community that the project is going to drown with the dot.com bubble as the 
traffic on the mailing list was fading steadily. That was the time when a few OpenORB community 
members decided to get more involved into the project. The movement was led by Steve McConnell and 
Michael Rumpf. The problem was trying to get Intalio to turn the OpenORB project into a real, 
i.e. community driven, open-source project after the example of many Apache projects. Unfortunately 
the strategy of getting Intalio into the boat was not successful. The consequence was a fork of 
the OpenORB project at SourceForge the <ulink url="http://openorb.sf.net">Community 
OpenORB</ulink>. The new project was founded by Steve McConnell, Michael Rumpf, Shawn Boyce, Jesper 
Pedersen, J. Scott Evans, and Viacheslav Tararin on January 8th 2002.</para>

<para>Soon after 
the formation of the Community OpenORB project version 1.2.1 of the OpenORB 
suite was released on January 11th 2002. This version included many bug-fixes over the Intalio 
source base that had been released on August 15th 2001 for the last time.
</para>

<para>
On June 8th 2002, Ashish Agrawal, VP. of Engineering at Intalio, Inc., send 
a mail to the open-source communities of the various projects that had been sponsored by Intalio 
over the past
<footnote>
<para>
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/message.php?msg_id=1671033">Mail from Ashish Agrawal,
VP. of Engineering at Intalio, Inc.</ulink>
</para>
</footnote>.
The part about OpenORB was: "We support the project on Sourceforge and recommend any 
contributors to contribute to this project. OpenORB will no longer be hosted on Exolab."
</para>

<para>
Since the beginning of the Community OpenORB project 
substantial changes have been made to the source base. 
Since early 2002 the circle of active developers grew to over 10, not including the people 
contributing patches eventually. The number of users, subscribed to the openorb-user 
mailing-list, grew to over 100, the downloads have passed 15.000.
On September 30th version 1.3.0 was released to the community.  
</para>
</section>

<section id="ch_intro_future">
<title>Future</title>
<para>
We are working to make OpenORB a part of the Apache project. We have already adopted the 
Apache community rules 
<footnote>
<para>
<ulink url="http://apache.org/foundation/">Apache Foundation</ulink>
</para>
</footnote>
and we are just waiting for the current copyright holder, Intalio, Inc., 
to donate the source base to the Apache Foundation.
Once the politics are completed we will move the project over to the Apache facilities making OpenORB a 
full member of the Apache Software community.
</para>

<para>
Independently of these efforts we are trying to make OpenORB the best open-source CORBA ORB around.
In order to achieve this goal we need your help. Either if you are a user, a technical writer, or 
a developer we will appreciate any help.
</para>

<para>
As a user you could help by answering other users's questions, by proposing new features, or by 
submitting bug reports.
</para>

<para>
Open-source projects often lack high quality documentation. New users depend on good documentation and
it definitely helps to reduce the traffic on the user mailing-list. So if you are good at writing 
documentation you are extremely welcome to join the team.
</para>

<para>
As a developer you can help by doing the usual things: fix bugs, add new features, write
test-cases, improve the build-system, or any other task of which you think should be improved.
</para>

<para>
This leads to the question: "How do I get involved?"
</para>
</section>

<section id="ch_intro_getinvolved">
<title>How to get involved</title>

<section id="ch_intro_getinvolved_user">
<title>User</title>
<para>
Although we are permanently trying to improve the documentation you may have problems using OpenORB.
In these cases you should follow the steps below:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Read this documentation and any related documentation carefully.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Search this module's FAQ and any related FAQs for answers to your questions.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Search the openorb-user mailing list
<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum_id=10381">archive</ulink></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If your question is more of a general CORBA question, then you should also search the
following newsgroup archives for answers: 
<ulink url="http://groups.google.de/groups?hl=de&amp;lr=&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;group=comp.object.corba">comp.object.corba</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://groups.google.de/groups?hl=de&amp;lr=&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;group=comp.lang.java.corba">comp.lang.java.corba</ulink>
.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If your problem can't be solved by any of the steps above, then send a question to the openorb-users
mailing-list. For spam protection the mailing-list has been restricted to subscribed members only. Therefore you need to
<ulink url="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/openorb-users">subscribe</ulink> to the mailing-list
before you can send your question. In order to receive qualified responses it is important that
your submission also passes a certain level of quality, i.e. include information like OS version, JDK version,
OpenORB module version, exception stack traces, or any other information that might be useful to analyze the problem.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
As an OpenORB user you are invited to share your knowledge with other community members when they are having problems.
When you know the
answer to another user's question feel free to respond to it. Doing so will help the developers, working on new features
or fixing bugs, to concentrate on these tasks. A vital community is a fundametal requirement for OpenORB becoming an
Apache project.
</para>
</section>

<section id="ch_intro_getinvolved_writer">
<title>Technical Writer</title>
<para>
As a technical writer you should be subscribed to the most important mailing lists: openorb-users and
openorb-devel. The questions sent to the openorb-users mailing-list are a good indicator of which part of the 
documentation needs to be improved.
The openorb-devel list is for internal development of the OpenORB modules and thus any discussion
about writing documentation for OpenORB should go here.
</para>

<para>
Documentation for the OpenORB modules is divided into two major parts, the docbook documentation and
the Javadoc documentation. The docbook documentation is created from XML files adhering to the docbook-xml
standard
<footnote>
<para>
Currently only HTML documentation is created from the XML source files. The PDF generation has recently
been disabled because the current <ulink url="http://xml.apache.org/fop/">Apache FOP</ulink> implementations,
both stable and dev, are having problems with the latest version of the docbook-xml and docbook-xsl combination.
</para>
</footnote>.
The second part is the Javadoc
documentation that is used for internal and external API documentation. Writing documentation includes
fixing or writing Javadoc comments, extending the docbook manual, and adding FAQ items.
</para>
</section>

<section id="ch_intro_getinvolved_developer">
<title>Developer</title>
<para>
As a developer you should be subscribed to both mailing lists: openorb-users and openorb-devel.
Any proposal for a new feature should be sent to the openorb-devel mailing list and will be discussed
by the members of these lists . As a developer you should know what the user thinks of a certain feature
 and therefore
subscription to the openorb-user mailing list is substantial. Another mailing-list that might be of
interest to a developer is the openorb-commits mailing-list. The CVS server is sending the diffs of
each cvs commit to this mailing-list. These notification mails keep you informed about what is going on
and it supports improving code quality because other members of the list can instantly review any patch that is
committed to the CVS tree.
</para>
</section>

</section>

</preface>

